<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dataroot export_time="Tue 22. Nov 12:16:14 2011" revision="43" export_branch="T:/branches/shogun2/boshin/shogun2/binaries" export_user="Richard.Aldridge">
<edit_uuid>ae2c706a-4207-4d36-8793-44b0e23980c4</edit_uuid><battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0001_TUT_Welcome</key>
<string>This a time of war: the Sengoku Jidai. Great lords battle for the soul of Japan. You must learn the arts of the warrior if you are to thrive. For now, you command Chosokabe Motochika's fiercest warriors. You must defeat the odious rebels.</string>
<title>Welcome</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0002_TUT_Select_Unit</key>
<string>We will start with the units in your army. Select the yari ashigaru by left-clicking on them or on the flashing unit card at the bottom of the screen.</string>
<title>Yari Ashigaru</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0003_TUT_Yari_Ashigaru_Info</key>
<string>Yari ashigaru are useful in any army. They carry spears - yari - and protect valuable units in battle, such as archers and other missile units. They also defend well against cavalry. Click on the tick button to continue.</string>
<title>Yari Ashigaru</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0003a_TUT_Advisor_Arrows</key>
<string>If you want to listen again to what I said, click on my portrait. Use the back and forward arrows to select advice. Now, when you are ready to continue click the tick button.</string>
<title>Advisor</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0004_TUT_Move_Yari_Ashigaru</key>
<string>There is a Chosokabe village further down the hillside. Select your yari ashigaru, and move there by right-clicking on the terrain.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0005_TUT_Walk_To_Run</key>
<string>Once you have ordered a unit to move, you can make it run or walk by pressing the R key. You can also click on the movement speed button.</string>
<title>Movement Speeds</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0006_TUT_Fatigue_Effects</key>
<string>All units are &quot;fresh&quot; when battle starts, but they will tire as they fight or move around the field. Running will tire a unit more than walking. It's important to keep units fresh. Being tired makes units fight poorly.</string>
<title>Fatigue</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0007_TUT_Unit_Halt</key>
<string>If you want to stop a unit carrying out its orders, click on the halt button.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0008_TUT_Reminder_Move</key>
<string>Excellent! You cancelled your unit's orders. Now, order the yari ashigaru towards the village again by right-clicking on the ground.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0009_TUT_Camera_WASD</key>
<string>The village has been overrun, and the attackers may still be nearby. Move the camera back to the yari ashigaru with the W, A, S and D keys, or double left-click on the unit card.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0010_TUT_Camera_QEZX</key>
<string>The camera can be moved up or down with the Z and X keys, or with your mouse roller button. Rotate the camera with Q and E. When you're ready, click on the new advice button.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0011_TUT_Camera_CV</key>
<string>You can also use the C and V keys to pivot the camera. Again, when you're ready click on the new advice button.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0012_TUT_Radar_Map</key>
<string>To help you defeat the enemy the radar map shows you the terrain and each army's troops. Your soldiers are yellow; your allies blue; and the enemy red. Your selected units are white. Be sure to watch out for enemy moves and tricks!</string>
<title>Radar Map</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0013_TUT_Unit_Rotation</key>
<string>A unit of katana cavalry are coming to attack your position. Turn and face them by selecting your yari ashigaru, then either clicking on the rotation arrows, or by holding down the right mouse button and dragging the unit out on the terrain in the direction you wish to face.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0015_TUT_Unit_Abilities</key>
<string>To improve your chances of withstanding the lethal charge of the katana cavalry, select the spear wall ability button. Your unit will adopt a special formation to inflict maximum casualties on the enemy. All battlefield units have their own abilities, so be sure to take advantage of them in battle.</string>
<title>Abilities</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0016_TUT_Morale_Effects</key>
<string>As a unit takes casualties their morale will start to drop, indicated by the coloured banner above them. Over time, this banner will change in colour from green to red. Once red, units are highly likely to rout and must be reinforced by more confident troops to prevent them fleeing the battlefield.</string>
<title>Morale</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0017_TUT_Cavalry_Success</key>
<string>Excellent! You have beaten the katana cavalry, and taken few casualties! Click the spear formation button again to turn it off. Use this tactic again when your spearmen face cavalry charges.</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0018_TUT_Power_Balance</key>
<string>The balance of power bar is above the radar map. It shows who is winning the battle. As units are destroyed or run away, the red and yellow displays change. With the enemy cavalry defeated, the red side is slightly smaller. Defeat all the rebels and all the bar will turn yellow.</string>
<title>Balance of Power</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0019_TUT_Reveal_Samurai_Archers</key>
<string>Now that the rebel cavalry are gone, some samurai archers have come out of hiding. Some units, like these archers, can hide in cover and then make surprise attacks. Move your yari ashigaru up behind your new archers. They will be useful in defeating the rebels.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0020_TUT_Samurai_Archers_Info</key>
<string>Archers allow you to inflict casualties from a distance. Archers should skirmish to keep their losses low, so click on the highlighted button. Skirmishing means that the archers will retreat to safety when enemies come too close. Once safe, they will fire again.</string>
<title>Samurai Archers</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0021_TUT_Unit_Formation</key>
<string>Keep your yari ashigaru near your archers to protect them and improve morale. Your position on the hill gives your men an advantage. Charging downhill will improve their attack. It can give an edge over highly trained enemies.</string>
<title>Formations</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0022_TUT_Firing_Arc</key>
<string>When selected all missile troops, including archers, have a firing arc shown to their front. Enemy units in this arc are targets as long as your warriors have ammunition. Now: watch as the enemy samurai advance on your archers!</string>
<title>Samurai Archers</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0023_TUT_Fire_At_Will</key>
<string>Your samurai archers can use different kinds of arrows. Select the fire arrow button to launch a devastating flaming attack!</string>
<title>Abilities</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0024_TUT_Ammo_Bar</key>
<string>Good! The rebels are hurt! Your archers have a limited supply of ammunition, so finish the rebels with the yari ashigaru. Select them now, and double right-click on the enemy samurai to charge!</string>
<title>Missile Resources</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0025_TUT_Charge_Bonus</key>
<string>Now order your units to move down towards the remaining enemy.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0026_TUT_Multi_Selection</key>
<string>Let the enemy flee! Now, select both your units by holding down the left mouse button and dragging a box around them.</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0027_TUT_Unit_Deselection</key>
<string>Don't forget the hill. Use this, and order your troops to run into position.</string>
<title>Movement Speeds</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0028_TUT_Heavy_Cavalry_Info</key>
<string>You now have some heavy cavalry. They are powerful, armoured, highly skilled and suited to hit-and-run fights. They can break the enemy's morale, and cause heavy casualties by bursting through their lines.</string>
<title>Heavy Cavalry</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0029_TUT_Cavalry_Charge</key>
<string>Select your heavy cavalry. Order them to attack the enemy archers. They are close, so charge the archers by double right-clicking.  This will minimise your losses and inflict maximum casualties on impact!</string>
<title>Charging</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0030_TUT_Speed_Settings</key>
<string>You can adjust the game speed to make battles quicker. This is very useful if you need to march a long way, and you want your troops to walk and stay fresh. You can also slow everything down and get a better look at the enemy. Experiment with the game speed as your troops move towards the village.</string>
<title>Game Speed</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0031_TUT_Fleeing_Troops</key>
<string>See! The rebels run for their lives! Finish off any stragglers! If they manage to escape routing units can sometimes regroup or reform as an army on the campaign map. Why leave a threat?</string>
<title>Routing</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0032_TUT_Victory</key>
<string>Most satisfactory! The rebels are defeated: a good start to the conquest of Shikoku!</string>
<title>Victory</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0033_TUT_Wedge</key>
<string>Before your cavalry reach the archers, click on the unit ability button and put them in wedge formation. This allows cavalry to cut through the enemies' ranks, and damages their morale.</string>
<title>Formations</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0034_TUT_Select_Archers</key>
<string>Left click on your archers, or their unit card, to select them.</string>
<title>Samurai Archers</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0101_TUT_Welcome</key>
<string>This is Sanuki province, the lands of the Sogo clan. They are powerful, but not to be feared! Here you will learn to use terrain correctly; deploy and use advanced units; outflank enemies; and inspire your men to win! Click on the tick button when you are ready.</string>
<title>Welcome</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0102_TUT_Deployment_Phase</key>
<string>Before battle, you deploy your army. You can use an attacking or defensive formation, and change the position of units within the deployment zone. You can also set up defences before battle starts.</string>
<title>Deployment</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0103_TUT_Deployment_Zones</key>
<string>The yellow box around your army on the ground, and the radar map, is its deployment zone. It is a good idea to place cavalry on the flanks, and put infantry in the centre. Lesser units, like ashigaru, should be in front so they can be the first casualties. Keep your general out of immediate danger.</string>
<title>Deployment Zones</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0104_TUT_Deployment_Generals</key>
<string>During deployment, the defender gets to see his enemy deploy before committing his own troops. As you are defending, carefully study how they have deployed and arrange your own units to confer maximum advantage. When ready, select the gong button to start the battle.</string>
<title>Generals </title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0105_TUT_Generals_Abilities</key>
<string>Your general is the focal point of the army: he directs and inspires his men. Your general automatically gives a small morale boost to troops inside his circle of influence. But he also has special abilities with greater effects too. Select your general now to learn more about these abilities.</string>
<title>Generals </title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0106_TUT_Generals_Abilities</key>
<string>Your general has an &quot;Inspire&quot; ability. This will increase a unit's morale, melee skills and missile accuracy, for a short period of time. He can also use the &quot;Rally&quot; ability, to stop troops from fleeing and boost the morale of nearby men. Be careful when you use these abilities: they cannot be used constantly, and you must wait before using them again. Picking the best time is part of being a skilful commander!</string>
<title>Generals </title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0107_TUT_Advance_Army</key>
<string>The Sogo clan are defending the far side of the river. We must control the nearby village, cross the river and attack! Move the army towards the village.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0108a_TUT_Move_Army</key>
<string>Your army can use predefined formations. To group them select all your units, then click on the group button followed by the lock button.</string>
<title>Army Selection</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0109_TUT_Village_Buildings</key>
<string>Scouting has revealed that the Sogo are in the village. Their troops are using the buildings for cover! Now, select your siege weapon.</string>
<title>Siege Weapons</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0110_TUT_Artillery_Units</key>
<string>Siege weapons are powerful, but don't move. They can attack targets from a distance, and have a firing arc that shows where they can fire. Siege weapons are inaccurate and easily routed, if left to look after themselves. Select the siege weapon and right click on the enemy to attack.</string>
<title>Siege Weapons</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0110a_TUT_Move_Artillery</key>
<string>Ha! The village is yours! Only the Sogo general and his best troops remain! They are on the distant hill. Use the cover of the forest to approach and attack the Sogo army. The trees will hide your men! Soon the Sogo lands will be yours!</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0110b_TUT_Move_Archers</key>
<string>Units such as matchlock ashigaru can fire on enemy buildings. They will cause less damage than a siege weapon, but might stop the enemy escaping.</string>
<title>Matchlock Ashigaru</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0110c_TUT_Artillery_Unlimber</key>
<string>Moveable siege weapons can only fire if they have been first been unlimbered. Select your siege weapon and then the limber/unlimber button. Its crew will set up it up to fire upon the building being used  for cover by the Sogo. If, at a later time, you wish to move the siege weapon to a new position, you must first limber your guns before issuing a move order.</string>
<title>Siege Weapons</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0111_TUT_No_Dachi_Samurai_Info</key>
<string>The enemy are weakened! It is time to assault the buildings with your no-dachi samurai!</string>
<title>No-dachi Samurai</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0112_TUT_Assault_Building</key>
<string>Elite no-dachi samurai carry two-handed swords. They are deadly in melee and have high morale, so they can fight away from your general. Select the no-dachi unit and right-click on the building to attack!</string>
<title>No-dachi Samurai</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0114_TUT_Musket_Ashigaru_Info</key>
<string>Matchlock ashigaru are peasants trained to use fire arms. They can decimate units when used en-masse. Forming them into wide rows ensures a large number of guns are presented in the direction they are facing, but their extremely poor melee capabilities and morale means matchlock ashigaru can be easily routed. Adverse weather conditions also cause major problems for them, as gunpowder weapons often malfunction in bad weather.</string>
<title>Matchlock Ashigaru</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0114b_TUT_Continue_Attack</key>
<string>Continue attacking the enemy building with your siege and missile units. Keep your cavalry and infantry units further back to avoid casualties.</string>
<title>Continue the Attack</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0115_TUT_River_Crossing</key>
<string>Now you control much of the village, cross the river and finish off the enemy. Order your men to wade at the ford or use the narrow bridge. Terrain plays an important part in battle, and sometimes the quickest route may not always be the best route to defeat the enemy!</string>
<title>River Crossings</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0116_TUT_Enemy_Forest</key>
<string>Enemy matchlock units are in the trees! Keep your cavalry back, as forests hinder them in a fight. So, select your naginata samurai units.</string>
<title>Forests</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0117_TUT_Naginata_Samurai_Info</key>
<string>Your fearsome naginata samurai carry polearms and wear impressive armour. They can protect your flanks and rear from cavalry. Their heavy armour means they can attack enemy missile units and not take many casualties.</string>
<title>Naginata Samurai</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0118_TUT_Group_Cavalry</key>
<string>While your infantry fight in the woods, select your yari cavalry.</string>
<title>Yari Cavalry</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0119_TUT_Groups</key>
<string>Your army has been formed into a group. Notice that their unit cards have been re-arranged under a group tab. Selecting the group tab will enable your army to move and attack whilst staying in formation. You can create as many groups as you like, but a unit can only be part of one group at any one time.</string>
<title>Groups </title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0120_TUT_Formations</key>
<string>Select the formation button and choose the formation that suits your needs. When ready, click the gong button to start the battle.</string>
<title>Army Formations</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0122_TUT_Yari_Cavalry_Info</key>
<string>Yari cavalry are the fastest units, used for scouting, outflanking and diversions. In wedge formation, they are good at hunting down unprotected missile units. Move your yari cavalry into position, ready to outflank the enemy!</string>
<title>Yari Cavalry</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0123_TUT_Hill_Advance</key>
<string>Excellent! The enemy matchlocks are no longer a problem! Finish the Sogo now: use the terrain and try to outflank the enemy!</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0124_TUT_Finish_Enemy</key>
<string>Now! Use your yari cavalry to charge the enemy matchlocks from behind. This should hurt morale, so that they rout from the battlefield.</string>
<title>Flank Attack</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0125_TUT_Victory</key>
<string>Congratulations, you have beaten the Sogo clan, and completed this tutorial.</string>
<title>Victory</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0127_TUT_Naginata_Attack</key>
<string>Charge the enemy units with your naginata samurai. Give them covering fire from your missile units!</string>
<title>Naginata Samurai</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0201_TUT_Welcome</key>
<string>Welcome to Total War: Shogun 2! This tutorial shows you how to use some of the new battlefield features in the game: castle capture points, hero units and key buildings. To start the tutorial, and siege the Miyoshi clan's castle, click on the &quot;tick&quot; button.</string>
<title>Welcome</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0202_TUT_Castles</key>
<string>When attacking a castle you must capture its keep, the &quot;tenshu&quot;. Capture that, and victory is automatic!</string>
<title>Castle Battles</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0203_TUT_Capture_Points</key>
<string>Now, use your army's specialist units to help capture the castle.</string>
<title>Castle Battles</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0204_TUT_Siege_Camp</key>
<string>Defenders must protect the tenshu at all costs: their castle towers can fend off an enemy attack. Total War: Shogun 2 contains many new units with new abilities. Some of these are in your army.</string>
<title>Castle Battles</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0205_TUT_Towers</key>
<string>The castle towers are still a threat to your troops. Towers can be captured by placing a unit next to them for a while. They are vital to controlling a castle: once yours, a tower will automatically fire arrows at the enemy! </string>
<title>Castle Towers</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0205a_TUT_Gates</key>
<string>You do not have to breach the castle walls. Order your kisho ninja and other infantry to climb the walls and take control of the gatehouses. That done, assault the enemy tenshu!</string>
<title>Castle Walls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0206a_TUT_Monk_Info</key>
<string>Warrior monks are fearsome in hand-to-hand combat. They have high morale, a charge bonus and fighting skills fuelled by religious fervour. Often, they will stand their ground despite casualties. Poor armour makes warrior monks vulnerable to missile attacks. Keep them away from archers when possible.</string>
<title>Warrior Monks</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0206b_TUT_Ninja_Info</key>
<string>Kisho ninja may assassinate an enemy general. They can hide on the battlefield and use blinding grenades to escape combat with better-armoured foes. Kisho ninja can also infiltrate castles. Their climbing claws make it easy to climb any wall and capture a gatehouse.</string>
<title>Kisho Ninja</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0206c_TUT_Hero_Info</key>
<string>Heroes are few in number, but can quickly cause heavy casualties. There are bow, katana and yari hero units.</string>
<title>Heroes</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0206d_TUT_Cavalry_Info</key>
<string>Cavalry units can dismount during battles. They can assault buildings and enter forests without the penalty of being mounted. Choosing to dismount at the right time is important, as the decision cannot be changed for a short time.</string>
<title>Cavalry</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0206e_TUT_Infantry_Info</key>
<string>Infantry units can use climbing claws to scale castle walls and infiltrate enemy tenshu. This ability works in the same way as the kisho ninja climbing ability, but at a much slower speed.</string>
<title>Infantry</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0207_TUT_Key_Buildings</key>
<string>One of your units is near a key building, which would be useful if captured. Cavalry will need to dismount before trying to take the building.</string>
<title>Key Buildings</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0207a_TUT_Key_Buildings</key>
<string>Although mostly found in multiplayer battles, key buildings give bonuses to nearby friendly units. They can replenish ammunition or restore morale. Any army can use key buildings and get their bonuses: just order a unit to enter, and then wait for the building to fall into your favour!</string>
<title>Key Buildings</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0208f_TUT_Buildings</key>
<string>Use key buildings to give bonuses to your troops before mounting an attack on the enemy castle. It is important to retain control of them, they are as useful to the enemy as to you.</string>
<title>Key Buildings</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0209_TUT_Zones</key>
<string>Inside a building there are zones where you can place units. The coloured markers show where units can stand, so you can select where to protect if attacked.</string>
<title>Buildings</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0210_TUT_Outro</key>
<string>The Myoshi are defeated! This tutorial is done.</string>
<title>Victory</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0301_TUT_Welcome</key>
<string>Welcome to Japan's Inland Sea. You have control of the Chosokabe fleet: these men are some of the finest sailors in Japan. Your task is to protect the Chosokabe trade routes from pirates and rival clans.</string>
<title>Welcome</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0302_TUT_Select_Ship</key>
<string>Left click on the bow ship to select it, or click on the flashing ship card at the bottom of the screen.</string>
<title>Bow Ship</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0303_TUT_Bow_Ship_Info</key>
<string>This is a bow ship, a small, fast moving vessel, essential to a balanced fleet. Its archers are best when they shoot fire arrows and set enemy ships alight. Many small ships used like this can stop heavier ships dead in the water, but they are vulnerable to boarding attacks.</string>
<title>Bow Ship</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0304b_TUT_Move_Bow_Ship</key>
<string>There is a ship on fire out to sea! This must be investigated! Move your bow ship: select it, and then right-click on the sea near the burning vessel.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0305b_TUT_Movement_Speeds</key>
<string>Your ship will now move at maximum speed to investigate. You can adjust the speed of the battle by using the game speed buttons above the radar.</string>
<title>Battle Speed</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0306b_TUT_Ship_Halt</key>
<string>If you go too close to the burning vessel the fire might spread to your ship. Click the drop anchor button to stop at a safe distance.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0307b_TUT_Waypoints</key>
<string>Excellent! The ship has stopped. It looks like the burning ship has hit a mine, and there are more floating around. You must avoid hitting them if the ship is to reach the open sea.</string>
<title>Mines</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0307c_TUT_Waypoints</key>
<string>Waypoints can safely guide the ship past the mines. Hold down the Shift key and then right-click on the sea away from the mines to create the first waypoint. Repeat this to make more waypoints and a route to safety.</string>
<title>Waypoints</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0308_TUT_Camera_WASD</key>
<string>You can reposition the camera by using the W, A, S and D keys now that your ship passed the mines. Or you can double click on the ship card to centre the camera on it.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0309_TUT_Camera_QEZX</key>
<string>The camera can be raised or lowered by using the Z and X keys or by the mouse wheel. It can be rotated using Q and E.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0310_TUT_Camera_CV</key>
<string>Finally, to pivot the camera to get a better battle view, use C and V.</string>
<title>Camera Controls</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0311_TUT_Radar_Map</key>
<string>The radar map shows the waters where you are fighting, including nearby land, shallows and the position of each fleet's ships. Your ships are shown in yellow; enemy ships are red.</string>
<title>Radar Map</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0312_TUT_Enemy_Ship</key>
<string>An enemy ship! Check its position on the radar map and prepare for battle!</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0313_TUT_Firing_Arcs</key>
<string>The coloured circle around your ship is your firing radius. It shows the maximum range of the ship's weapons. Try to position your ship so that the enemy moves into your firing radius. Keep at a safe distance: they could board if they get too close.</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0314_TUT_Ship_Rotation</key>
<string>The rotation buttons let you turn a ship on the spot, so that many of your archers can fire at the enemy. You can also right-click on the enemy ship. Your ship will continue to fire on the enemy until you give it a new order.</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0315_TUT_Fire_Arrows</key>
<string>Ships can cause extra damage by using their abilities: this bow ship can use the fire arrows. They cause more damage than ordinary arrows, and can set an enemy on fire. Now: select the fire arrow button to use them.</string>
<title>Abilities</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0316_TUT_Health_Bars</key>
<string>The enemy ship is damaged and it has crew casualties: the sashimono flags above the ship are now tattered and worn. They show the strength of the ship's hull and the damage you have caused.</string>
<title>Damage</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0317_TUT_Morale</key>
<string>Crew morale begins to fail when their ship is damaged. As the coloured banner above a ship changes from green to red it will eventually try to flee. To stop this, keep your ships together; repair their hulls when they are damaged.</string>
<title>Morale</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0317a_TUT_Attack_Enemy</key>
<string>Keep attacking the enemy ship. Right-click on it to issue attack orders; keep it within your firing arc to cause maximum damage!</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0317b_TUT_Enemy_Destroyed</key>
<string>Thank the sea-spirits! The enemy is defeated!</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0318_TUT_New_Course</key>
<string>With the enemy beaten, head out to sea and look for other vessels along the coast. Right-click on the sea to set a new course.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0319_TUT_Assistance</key>
<string>A stranded allied ship has been spotted. Head towards it to give assistance.</string>
<title>Movement</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0320_TUT_Ship_Added</key>
<string>Good! The stranded ship has joined your fleet, but it is damaged. To repair it, left-click the ship or select the medium bune ship card. </string>
<title>Medium Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0321_TUT_Repair_Button</key>
<string>Now click on the repair ship button. The crew will begin work.</string>
<title>Repairs</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0322_TUT_Repair_Process</key>
<string>Your ship cannot do anything else while it is being repaired, unless you cancel the work. Once the repairs are completed the ship is ready for combat. Let the crew finish the repairs; we will look at the bune's strengths and weaknesses.</string>
<title>Repairs</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0323_TUT_Med_Bune_Info</key>
<string>Bunes come in medium and large sizes. This is a medium bune, a good all-rounder.  It has excellent speed, manoeuvrability and hull strength. It protects smaller vessels, like the bow ship, and can board and capture equivalent enemy vessels.</string>
<title>Medium Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0324_TUT_Grouping</key>
<string>It is easier to protect a fleet when the ships are grouped. Select all your ships: left click and drag a box around them; you can also hold down the control key and left-click on their ship cards.</string>
<title>Groups</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0324a_TUT_Grouping</key>
<string>Now click on the group button to form them into a group. You can create as many groups as you wish if you have enough ships.</string>
<title>Groups</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0325_TUT_Group_Formed</key>
<string>Look: your ship cards have been grouped under a single tab. Single ships can still be selected and given orders, but you can click on the tab and give orders to all the ships at once.</string>
<title>Groups</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0326_TUT_Formations</key>
<string>You can put grouped ships into formations. Click on the group tab of the group you wish to arrange. Formations are shown at the edge of the screen. Picking one orders the ships to arrange themselves into that chosen formation.</string>
<title>Formations</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0327_TUT_Hev_Bune_info</key>
<string>Help has arrived: a heavy bune has joined your fleet. This is a slow-moving ship with a large crew, containing a few missile troops. A heavy bune is very effective in boarding attacks, but not very manoeuvrable. It is also vulnerable to fire damage.</string>
<title>Heavy Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0328_TUT_Enemy_Ships</key>
<string>There are enemy ships further up the coast! Move to intercept them!</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0329_TUT_Boarding</key>
<string>You have a heavy bune in your fleet while the enemy only have medium-sized ships. A boarding attack would be good! Select your heavy bune.</string>
<title>Heavy Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0329a_TUT_Boarding</key>
<string>Click on the boarding button and then right-click on one of the enemy ships to issue a boarding attack!</string>
<title>Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0330_TUT_Boarding_Started</key>
<string>Your heavy bune will move to within boarding range of its target. Once alongside, troops from your vessel will board and attempt to take the ship!</string>
<title>Boarding</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0331_TUT_Boarding_BOP</key>
<string>As crew and boarders are killed, the morale of the living falls until one side surrenders. If you are losing, select your bune, and then click on the &quot;war cry&quot; ability.</string>
<title>Boarding</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0331b_TUT_Warcry</key>
<string>&quot;War cry&quot; boosts your crew's morale and fighting skills. Now, the enemy will soon be feeding the fishes!</string>
<title>Abilities</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0332_TUT_Enemy_Surrendered</key>
<string>Good! The enemy crew have surrendered! Their vessel is yours! Finish off the other enemy ships!</string>
<title>Combat Success</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0333_TUT_Outro</key>
<string>Most excellent! You have completed the tutorial, and protected the clan's valuable trade!</string>
<title>Victory</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0401_TUT_Welcome</key>
<string>Welcome to Total War: Shogun 2. This tutorial will show you some of the exciting new naval features in the game: shallow waters, cannon ships and mines!</string>
<title>Welcome</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0402_TUT_Deployables</key>
<string>You can use deployable weapons in naval battles. Mines are small wooden platforms carrying explosives that damage unsuspecting ships. Your fire bomb ship can place mines anywhere during deployment, but not in the enemy deployment zone. Select the fire bomb ship.</string>
<title>Mines</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0403_TUT_Deployables</key>
<string>Now, right-click on the sea where you want your ship to deploy a mine. Once battle starts, mines are not under your control, so position them for maximum destructive effect! When you are happy click on the place mine button.</string>
<title>Mines</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0404_TUT_Sea_Mine</key>
<string>Ha! Your first mine is ready!</string>
<title>Mines</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0405_TUT_Place_Deployables</key>
<string>Before the battle begins you can change your mines' positions. Click on the remove mines button and then place them again. Finish placing your mines before starting the battle.</string>
<title>Mines</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406_TUT_Ship_Types</key>
<string>Before the fighting starts, we'll look at some of the ships in Total War: Shogun2.</string>
<title>Ships</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406a_TUT_Cannon_Bune</key>
<string>The cannon bune is fast-moving for hit-and-run attacks against larger vessels. It should be kept away from medium and large ships to avoid boarding actions. If boarding is likely, a cannon bune can use its &quot;fast rowing&quot; to make a quick escape.</string>
<title>Cannon Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406b_TUT_Matchlock_Ship</key>
<string>Matchlock ships are small and fast-moving. They are deadly to enemy crews. Keep them safely away from larger ships; they are vulnerable to boarding. Matchlocks will also suffer if attacked by siege tower ships because their upper decks lack cover.</string>
<title>Matchlock Ship</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406c_TUT_Fire_Bomb_Ship</key>
<string>Fire bomb ships use horoku bombs to cause serious damage at close range, but are easily boarded and taken. Speed and crew numbers mean that they are best used to hit-and-run. They have little cover on the deck, and will suffer if attacked by missiles.</string>
<title>Fire Bomb Ship</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406d_TUT_Siege_Tower_Ship</key>
<string>Siege tower ships use superior height to rain down terror! The top deck tower allows them to kill enemy crews easily. Despite their speed and manoeuvrability, siege tower ships are weak in boarding actions, or if they take too much fire damage.</string>
<title>Siege Tower Ship</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406e_TUT_Sengoku_Bune</key>
<string>The sengoku bune is the only Japanese sailing ship, making it the fastest in the fleet. It is ideal for catching and boarding small vessels. The sengoku bune carries fewer crew than other medium-sized ships, leaving them vulnerable to near-equals.</string>
<title>Sengoku Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406f_TUT_O_Ataka_Bune</key>
<string>The o ataka bune is a bigger, better ataka bune! It has the largest crew of any ship, and it attacks by boarding.  However, it is slow and manoeuvres badly, so can be sunk by missile ships.</string>
<title>O Ataka Bune</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406g_TUT_Nihon_Maru</key>
<string>The Nihon Maru is the shogun's flagship, and the jewel of any fleet. You can only have it once your daimyo is shogun. It boosts the morale of all nearby ships and has a large crew, but the Nihon Maru is slow, cumbersome and susceptible to fire damage.</string>
<title>Nihon Maru</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>battle_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406h_TUT_Caravel</key>
<string>The caravel uses eastern and western design ideas, its European cannons make it lethal when firing from afar. But its crew is susceptible to boarding attacks.</string>
<title>Caravel</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0406i_TUT_Set_Sail</key>
<string>So, you have a magnificent fleet! Destroy the approaching Myoshi!</string>
<title>Naval Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0407_TUT_Sea_Terrain</key>
<string>For the first time in Total War, sea battles include terrain. As the map shows, there are islands, coasts and shallow waters: all of these can be used tactically with your ships' capabilities.</string>
<title>Sea Terrain</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0408_TUT_Land_Mass</key>
<string>Land, the islands and coastline, is impassable for ships. Land can be useful for trapping enemies or shielding your vessels. Land masses are shown the radar map as green areas.</string>
<title>Sea Terrain</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0409_TUT_Shallow_Water</key>
<string>Shallow waters, highlighted by the sea's light blue colour, give missile ships the advantage over their larger enemies. Shallow waters are impassable to ships, but missile fire can cross them.</string>
<title>Sea Terrain</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0411_TUT_Weather</key>
<string>The time and weather also make a difference in naval battles. Rain affects missiles; boarding attacks are more important in the rain.</string>
<title>Weather</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0412_TUT_Boarding</key>
<string>Boarding actions are now possible on either or both sides of an enemy ship, giving the boarders potentially twice the crew of the defenders. A ship defending against boarders can also reinforce themselves with another friendly vessel and crew. A maximum of three ships can be locked together at any time during a boarding action.</string>
<title>Boarding</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
<battle_script_advice_strings>
<advisor_name>naval_advisor</advisor_name>
<key>CreativeAssembly.0414_TUT_Outro</key>
<string>Now, feel free to try out your new ships, and their special capabilities, against the enemy fleet.</string>
<title>Naval Combat</title>
</battle_script_advice_strings>
</dataroot>