<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<dataroot export_time="Tue 20. Dec 15:21:03 2011" revision="85" export_branch="C:/TotalWar/branches/shogun2/boshin/common/TWeak/Framework" export_user="Paul.Kitchin">
<edit_uuid>601e3b05-93d4-45f0-a652-8a5d9362fe5b</edit_uuid><message_event_text>
<key>agent_convalesced</key>
<text>Rest and reflection mean this agent is now restored to full health and awaiting fresh orders at the clan capital.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_dies_army</key>
<text>This agent died following the destruction of the army to which they were assigned.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_dies_navy</key>
<text>This agent died following the destruction of the navy to which they were assigned.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_dies_suspicious</key>
<text>The events surrounding this agent's death are decidedly suspicious. There is blood on the hands of our enemies.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_dies_suspicious_female</key>
<text>One of our agents met her end under suspicious circumstances. There is no mistaking the hand of the enemy in this event.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_enemy_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy geisha was trapped and dealt with. She no longer poses a threat to the safety of the clan...or anyone else for that matter.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_enemy_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>The enemy succeeded in their assassination attempt. Having stolen this character's life, their geisha has slipped away into the night.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_enemy_assassin_fail</key>
<text>A murderous geisha was detected. She was unable to complete her bloody task. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_enemy_assassin_success</key>
<text>Alas! An enemy geisha succeeded in wounding this character. Luckily they have escaped with their life and continue to serve the clan. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_enemy_detected</key>
<text>The enemy sent a geisha amongst us! Through the vigilance of our men she was rooted out before any damage was done.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_yours_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>Dishonour! Our geisha failed in her mission and was executed by the enemy. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_yours_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>Our geisha successfully killed her target. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_yours_assassin_fail</key>
<text>Our geisha failed to complete her task and was detected by the enemy. It will not end well for her.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_kun_yours_assassin_success</key>
<text>This geisha failed us, having managed only to wound her target.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_apprehension_critical_fail</key>
<text>We will not suffer others to meter out false justice in our lands. An enemy metsuke was apprehended and killed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_apprehension_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy metsuke had our agent executed, having implicated them in crimes against the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_apprehension_fail</key>
<text>Another's so-called justice has little sway here! An enemy metsuke failed to indict one of our agents.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_apprehension_success</key>
<text>A travesty of justice effected by the enemy led to the imprisonment of one of our agents. As the sentence is short they will return to service soon.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_bribe_critical_fail</key>
<text>This metsuke was attempting to bribe one of our clan members. He has paid for this impudence with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_bribe_fail</key>
<text>The respect our men have for the daimyo prevented the enemy from bribing them into his service.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_enemy_bribe_success</key>
<text>Dishonour! This character has gone over to the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_apprehension_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our metsuke failed to inculpate an enemy agent and has himself been put to the sword.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_apprehension_critical_success</key>
<text>Our metsuke apprehended an enemy agent. They were successfully charged with heinous misdeeds and put to death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_apprehension_fail</key>
<text>An enemy agent escaped the grasp of our metsuke.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_apprehension_success</key>
<text>An enemy agent was apprehended by our metsuke. Whilst insufficient evidence was found to incriminate them, they were, nonetheless, temporarily imprisoned. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_bribe_critical_fail</key>
<text>This man failed us. He was caught attempting to bribe the enemy and was summarily put to death. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_bribe_fail</key>
<text>This man doesn't even have the wits to bribe a soldier! He failed us, let us hope this isn't a common occurrence. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_met_yours_bribe_success</key>
<text>It seems that even the most virtuous have their price! Our agent used his silver tongue to charm the enemy and bring them around to our way of thinking.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>The enemy sent its missionary into our midst to demoralise the men. We have taken his life as an example to others.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>An enemy missionary was found amongst the army, attempting to demoralise the men. He failed in his despicable task.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>This army was demoralised by the words of an enemy missionary.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy missionary was executed as punishment for trying to incite insurrection. His kind will not be tolerated. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_incitement_fail</key>
<text>The enemy's attempts to incite a revolt here have failed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_incitement_success</key>
<text>This settlement has been stirred to revolt! An enemy missionary has been spreading lies amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>This enemy missionary attempted to persuade our agents to desert their beliefs. He has faced death for his crime.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>Our agent was successfully tempted to renounce his beliefs by an enemy missionary.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>The enemy failed to persuade this agent to renounce his beliefs.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_enemy_persuasion_success</key>
<text>An enemy missionary converted the weak mind of our agent to his false religion.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>Whilst attempting to spread the word of God this agent was executed by the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>Our missionary failed to spread dissent amongst the ranks of the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>The enemy army is wracked with doubt thanks to the efforts of our agent. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our missionary was executed in the course of his duty, having failed to incite rebellion amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_incitement_fail</key>
<text>No amount of careful persuasion could convince the people of this settlement to rebel against their masters. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_incitement_success</key>
<text>A few carefully chosen words can bring an entire settlement to its knees. Our agent successfully incited revolt here.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our missionary was captured and executed whilst attempting to convert an enemy agent.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>Following discourse with our missionary, an enemy agent saw sense and renounced his old ways.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>Not all are ready to accept the word of God. Our missionary failed to  convert an enemy agent.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mis_yours_persuasion_success</key>
<text>Our missionary forced an enemy agent to reconsider his beliefs.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monk was captured attempting to demoralise our troops. He was executed as an example to others. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>Despite enemy attempts to demoralise the army it remains ready to fight to the bitter end.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>Our army was demoralised by an enemy agent.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>The enemy sent a religious man to spread poison through the army. Having failed, his life is now forfeit. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_incitement_fail</key>
<text>An enemy agent attempted to seed dissention amongst the people, but their loyalty to the clan never faltered.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_incitement_success</key>
<text>The people are beginning to doubt the clan leadership, an enemy agent having spread dissent amongst them. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>The downfall of this enemy agent was his failure to defeat the resolve of our own. He was executed for the crime.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>One of our agents turned his back on the clan, accepting the lies of the enemy as truth.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>Despite the best efforts of the enemy this agent stuck to their convictions.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_enemy_persuasion_success</key>
<text>Having had a crisis of conscience this agent retreated to a place of solitude. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our monk was caught moving amongst an enemy army and executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>Our monk failed to spread discontent amongst the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>Words can be as powerful as the sword. Our monk caused the enemy troops to doubt their leadership.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>This monk was executed for inciting unrest amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_incitement_fail</key>
<text>No amount of careful persuasion could convince the people of this settlement to rebel against their masters. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_incitement_success</key>
<text>Chaos reigns! Our monk successfully incited revolt in this settlement.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our monk was executed for trying to persuade an enemy agent to give up his vocation.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>A man uncertain of his beliefs is easy to lead astray. Our monk successfully convinced an enemy agent to abandon his cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>Some are too narrow minded to reach for enlightenment. We failed to broaden this enemy agent's mind.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_mon_yours_persuasion_success</key>
<text>An enemy agent retired to consider the difficult path to enlightenment.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_recruited</key>
<text>An agent has been recruited to aid our cause.\n\n</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_released</key>
<text>The enemy released our agent from imprisonment. They returned to the capital and are ready to serve the clan once more.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_returns</key>
<text>Following a period of religious contemplation, our agent returned refreshed and ready to serve at the capital.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>agent_sensei_level</key>
<text>Devotion to one's calling leads to greatness. This sensei's achievements will prove beneficial to the whole clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>alliance_broken</key>
<text>The alliance between these two great clans was broken.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>alliance_broken_yours</key>
<text>Although our friendship is not lightly cast aside, the alliance between us is over.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>alliance_declared</key>
<text>These two clans elected to form an alliance. This agreement will strengthen them both.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>alliance_declared_yours</key>
<text>We successfully forged an alliance with another clan, strengthening us both.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>ambusher_discovered_theirs</key>
<text>Deception! An army was discovered lying in ambush for an unsuspecting enemy force.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>ambusher_discovered_yours</key>
<text>Our hidden army was spotted by forces belonging to another clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>attrition_high_seas</key>
<text>The capricious waves claimed crew members from our fleet.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>attrition_winter</key>
<text>The bitter cold took its toll on our troops, some of whom did not survive the winter.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>black_ship_captured</key>
<text>The European trade ship is now ours, my lord, a ship that will ensure our mastery of the waves. It was found to be carrying a number of goods and treasures that have now been returned to the capital.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>black_ship_sighted</key>
<text>My lord! A great vessel cuts an eastward path towards Japan, a mighty European trade ship wielding more destructive power than anything we can build. We should hunt down and capture this black ship for ourselves. To possess such a ship would render us indomitable at sea!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_army_critical_fail</key>
<text>A rival geisha was captured and executed whilst attempting to distract our troops.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_army_critical_success</key>
<text>Some men's hearts are weak. A rival geisha successfully distracted our troops.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_army_fail</key>
<text>A rival geisha was seen attempting to distract our troops. Utterly devoted to their duty, they were not swayed by her performance.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_garrison_critical_fail</key>
<text>Having attempted to distract a garrison from their duty, a rival geisha was caught and executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_garrison_critical_success</key>
<text>The weakness of men knows no bounds. Some of our garrisoned forces have been distracted by a rival geisha.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_distract_garrison_fail</key>
<text>A rival geisha has been seen in one of our towns, attempting to distract the local garrison. Unswayed by her performance, they have remained steadfast.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_enchant_critical_fail</key>
<text>A woman's wiles cannot sway loyalty to one's lord. This enemy geisha was executed for attempting to enchant one of our subjects.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_enchant_critical_success</key>
<text>Deplorable! One of our subjects was enchanted by an enemy geisha. Now he serves her lord.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_geisha_enchant_fail</key>
<text>An enemy geisha  attempted to seduce one of our subjects. Loyalty has prevailed, but we must be vigilant.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy ishin shishi attempted to assassinate one of our subjects. He has been caught and executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy ishin shishi has assassinated one of our subjects. This will not stand!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_assassin_fail</key>
<text>An assassination attempt has been made against us! The perpetrator is still at large but must be dealt with.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_assassin_success</key>
<text>One of our subjects has been wounded in an assassination attempt by an enemy ishin shishi.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_incite_revolt_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy ishin shishi was executed as punishment for trying to incite insurrection. Dissidents will not be tolerated. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_incite_revolt_critical_success</key>
<text>This settlement has been stirred to revolt! An enemy ishin shishi has been spreading lies amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_incite_revolt_fail</key>
<text>The enemy's attempts to incite a revolt here have failed; we must see to it that they do not try again.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_persuade_troops_critical_fail</key>
<text>An ishin shishi has been caught trying to foster betrayal amongst our troops. He has been silenced.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_persuade_troops_critical_success</key>
<text>Treachery! Swayed by ishin shishi lies, our troops have abandoned our cause and joined the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_ishin_persuade_troops_fail</key>
<text>Our men know well where their loyalties lie; an enemy ishin shishi has failed to secure their betrayal.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was apprehended and executed following an assassination attempt.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>One of our subjects met their end under suspicious circumstances. There is no mistaking the hand of the enemy in this event.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_assassin_detected</key>
<text>Our men detected the presence of a rival shinobi. We must be cautious.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_assassin_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was detected whilst attempting the assassination of a man loyal to our clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_assassin_success</key>
<text>The enemy attempted to assassinate a member of our clan! Having succeeded only in wounding them, the assassin has now escaped. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_army_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage our army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_army_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi successfully sabotaged our army. This is an outrage!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_army_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was spotted moving amongst the men! Early detection prevented any misfortune from befalling the army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_building_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage one of our buildings.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_building_critical_success</key>
<text>A building was sabotaged by an enemy shinobi. The culprit escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinobi_sabotage_building_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinobi was detected attempting to sabotage our building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinsengumi attempted to assassinate one of our subjects. He has been caught and executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy shinsengumi has assassinated one of our subjects. This will not stand!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_assassin_fail</key>
<text>An assassination attempt has been made against us! The perpetrator is still at large and must be dealt with.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_assassin_success</key>
<text>One of our subjects has been wounded in an assassination attempt by an enemy shinsengumi.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_coerce_troops_critical_fail</key>
<text>A shinsengumi was caught attempting to coerce our troops to join him. He will bother us no longer.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_coerce_troops_critical_success</key>
<text>Weakness! Our troops were coerced by an enemy shinsengumi, abandoning our cause for treachery.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_coerce_troops_fail</key>
<text>Our men do not fear empty threats; an enemy shinsengumi has failed to coerce their joining of his cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_incite_revolt_critical_fail</key>
<text>The enemy sent a shinsengumi to foster dissent in our province. With failure his life is forfeit.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_incite_revolt_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy shinsengumi spread dissent throughout this province! The people have risen against us!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_shinsen_incite_revolt_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shinsengumi attempted to seed dissention amongst our people, but their loyalty never faltered.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_duel_critical_fail</key>
<text>A foreign veteran challenged one of our own to single combat. His skills were no match; he died with honour.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_duel_critical_success</key>
<text>Inconceivable! One of our subjects fell in single combat against a foreign veteran!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_duel_fail</key>
<text>A foreign veteran challenged one of our own to single combat. Honourless in the face of defeat, he fled from the duel.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_duel_success</key>
<text>A foreign veteran has bested one of our subjects in single combat, both wounding and dishonouring him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_harass_critical_fail</key>
<text>We have captured a foreign veteran attempting to harass our forces. He has been put to the sword.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_harass_critical_success</key>
<text>Our forces have been harassed by a foreign veteran! Many have died and the men are in dissaray!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_harass_fail</key>
<text>A foreign veteran has attempted to harass our forces! Unable to cause casualties, he managed to evade capture.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_sabotage_building_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy foreign veteran was captured and executed for attempting the sabotage of a building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_sabotage_building_critical_success</key>
<text>A building was sabotaged by an enemy foreign veteran. He has managed to evade capture.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_enemy_veteran_sabotage_building_fail</key>
<text>A foreign veteran was seen attempting to sabotage a building. He was unsuccessful yet managed to evade capture.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_army_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our geisha failed to distract the rival army and was executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_army_critical_success</key>
<text>Our geisha successfully distracted the rival army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_army_fail</key>
<text>Our geisha failed to distract the rival army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_garrison_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our geisha was executed for attempting to distract an enemy garrison from their duty.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_garrison_critical_success</key>
<text>The predictability of men! Our geisha successfully distracted part of an enemy garrison.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_distract_garrison_fail</key>
<text>Our geisha failed to distract an enemy garrison.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_enchant_critical_fail</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our geisha was murdered for attempting to enchant an enemy subject.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_enchant_critical_success</key>
<text>Our geisha successfully seduced an enemy. He has abandoned his former master and sworn himself to our cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_enchant_fail</key>
<text>Not all are swayed by a lady's charm. Our geisha falied to enchant an enemy subject.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_geisha_level_up</key>
<text>This geisha is ready to perfect her skills, having developed her performing art.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our ishin shishi failed to assassinate his target. He was murdered whilst attempting to escape.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>Driven by zeal, our ishin shishi successfully eliminated his target.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_assassin_fail</key>
<text>Our ishin shishi failed to eliminate his target, but evaded capture and death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_assassin_success</key>
<text>Although unable to kill his target, our ishin shishi still managed to wound and temporarily put them out of action.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_incite_revolt_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our ishin shishi was executed for attempting to incite unrest amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_incite_revolt_critical_success</key>
<text>Chaos reigns! Our ishin shishi successfully incited revolt in this settlement.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_incite_revolt_fail</key>
<text>No amount of careful persuasion could convince the people of this settlement to rebel against their masters. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_level_up</key>
<text>Having resolved to return power to the Emperor, this ishin shishi is ready to develop his skills in anger.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_persuade_troops_critical_fail</key>
<text>Failure! Caught attempting to persuade enemy forces to join us, our ishin shishi was executed. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_persuade_troops_critical_success</key>
<text>Even the most loyal of spirits can be swayed! Our ishin shishi successfully persuaded rival forces to join our cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_ishin_persuade_troops_fail</key>
<text>This man lacks even the conviction to persuade a common soldier! Let us hope this isn't a common occurrence. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi failed to eliminate his target. He was caught and executed whilst trying to escape.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>Our shinobi successfully assassinated his target, using all the cunning and skill available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_assassin_detected</key>
<text>Our shinobi was detected by agents of another clan. He may now be vulnerable to their machinations.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_assassin_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi failed to eliminate his target and was detected, managing to escape the clutches of the enemy and a certain death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_assassin_success</key>
<text>Although unable to kill his target, our shinobi wounded his adversary, temporarily putting him out of action.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_level_up</key>
<text>Having developed a talent for subterfuge, this shinobi is ready to master his skills.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_army_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi failed to sabotage his target army. He was caught and executed out-of-hand. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_army_critical_success</key>
<text>Our shinobi succeeded in sabotaging the enemy army and escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_army_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi failed to sabotage the enemy army and was detected, barely managing to escape with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_building_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi failed to sabotage his target. He was captured and summarily executed. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_building_critical_success</key>
<text>Our shinobi successfully sabotaged his target, using all the subversive skills available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinobi_sabotage_building_fail</key>
<text>Our shinobi has been detected whilst attempting to sabotage an enemy building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shinsengumi failed to eliminate his target. He was killed whilst attempting to escape.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>Through diligence and skill, our shinsengumi successfully assassinated his target.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_assassin_fail</key>
<text>Our shinsengumi failed to eliminate his target, but managed to evade capture and death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_assassin_success</key>
<text>Our shinsengumi wounded his target, although he was unable to kill them. They have been temporarily put out of action.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_coerce_troops_critical_fail</key>
<text>This man failed us. Caught attempting to coerce enemy forces to join us, he was summarily put to death. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_coerce_troops_critical_success</key>
<text>Even the most fearless of spirits can be broken! Our shinsengumi cold-heartedly coerced rival forces to join us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_coerce_troops_fail</key>
<text>This man lacks the ruthlessness to coerce even the weakest of soldiers! He must not fail us again. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_incite_revolt_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shinsengumi was executed in the course of his duty, having failed to incite rebellion amongst the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_incite_revolt_critical_success</key>
<text>A few carefully chosen words can bring an entire settlement to its knees. Our shinsengumi successfully incited revolt here.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_incite_revolt_fail</key>
<text>No amount of careful persuasion could convince the people of this settlement to rebel against their masters. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_shinsen_level_up</key>
<text>Having resolved to support the Shogun until death, this shinsengumi is ready to develop his skills in anger.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_duel_critical_fail</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our foreign veteran has fallen in single combat against the enemy!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_duel_critical_success</key>
<text>This is an auspicious day! Our foreign veteran fought with honour and killed his enemy in single combat.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_duel_fail</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran was defeated by his opponent in single combat, barely managing to escape with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_duel_success</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran managed to wound his enemy in single combat, thereby forcing him to flee in shame and fear.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_harass_critical_fail</key>
<text>Having failed to harass enemy forces, our foreign veteran was captured and killed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_harass_critical_success</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran successfully harassed an enemy army, bringing death and disarray to them.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_harass_fail</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran failed to harass enemy forces, barely managing to escape with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_level_up</key>
<text>This foreign veteran is ready to refine his skills, having long-developed his craft. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_sabotage_building_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran was captured and executed trying to sabotage an enemy building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_sabotage_building_critical_success</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran used skill and cunning to sabotage his target building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_agent_yours_veteran_sabotage_building_fail</key>
<text>Our foreign veteran was spotted attempting to sabotage an enemy building and had to abandon his mission.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_attrition_bombardment</key>
<text>One of our fleets has been damaged by enemy coastal defences.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_camp_rebellion</key>
<text>This ungrateful populace have taken up arms against their rightful masters!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_camp_rebellion_imperial</key>
<text>Radical Imperialists in this province have risen up in revolt against us!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_camp_rebellion_samurai</key>
<text>Enraged at the loss of traditional values, samurai in this province have risen up in revolt!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_camp_rebellion_shogun</key>
<text>Seditious Shogunate loyalists in this province have risen up in revolt against us!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campaign_won</key>
<text>Glorious! We have triumphed over adversity and succeeded in uniting the people of Japan; a new era of progress and prosperity awaits!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_allegiance_convert_emperor</key>
<text>After lengthy consideration we have abandoned the Shogunate and committed our forces to the Emperor. Undoubtedly there will be repercussions for months to come.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_allegiance_convert_self</key>
<text>After lengthy consideration we have chosen to abandon both the Emperor and the Shogunate, establishing an independent republic with which to forge our own destiny.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_allegiance_convert_shogun</key>
<text>After lengthy consideration we have abandoned the Emperor and committed our forces to the Shogun. Undoubtedly there will be repercussions during the months ahead.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_minor_clan_defects_imperial</key>
<text>The daimyo of this clan has abandoned the Emperor and thrown his lot in with the Shogunate! Such treachery will not stand!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_minor_clan_defects_shogun</key>
<text>The daimyo of this clan has turned his back on the Shogun and defected to the Imperialists! Such treachery will not stand!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_minor_clan_joins_imperial</key>
<text>Seeing the futility of the Shogun's struggle, the daimyo of this clan has wisely chosen to abandon his former lord and support the Emperor.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_minor_clan_joins_shogun</key>
<text>Seeing folly in the Emperor's bid for control, the daimyo of this clan has wisely chosen to abandon his former lord and fight for the rightful Shogunate.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_1_imperial</key>
<text>In return for service to the Emperor, you have been granted the rank of junior councillor to the Court.\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of inspector general.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_1_shogun</key>
<text>In return for service to the Shogunate, you have been granted the rank of governor within the Bakufu.\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of inspector general.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_2_imperial</key>
<text>Our continued support of the Emperor pleases the Court greatly; for your efforts you have been promoted to senior councillor.\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of comptroller.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_2_shogun</key>
<text>Our continued support of the Shogun pleases the Bakufu greatly; for your efforts, you have been promoted to young elder!\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of comptroller.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_3_imperial</key>
<text>Our clan grows strong, ever loyal to the Emperor's cause. In recognition of your long service, you have been promoted to chancellor of state!\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of chief of staff.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_3_shogun</key>
<text>Our clan grows strong, ever loyal to the Shogun's cause. In recognition of your service, he has made you an elder.\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of chief of staff.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_4_imperial</key>
<text>The civil war rages on, and our achievements in the Emperor's name have been without equal. In honour of your loyalty and dilligence, he has declared you regent!\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of commander-in-chief.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_prestige_level_4_shogun</key>
<text>The civil war rages on, and our achievements in the Shogun's name have been without equal. In honour of your loyalty and dilligence, he has named you great elder!\n\nYou may now appoint a general to the office of commander-in-chief.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_coal</key>
<text>We have secured a source of coal. We can develop a railway network, technology permitting.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_copper</key>
<text>We have secured a source of copper, enabling the production of strong ships.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_cotton</key>
<text>We have secured a source of cotton, enabling the development of our our textiles industry.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_iron</key>
<text>We have secured a source of iron, enabling the production of the strongest ships and armour.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_machinery</key>
<text>We have secured modern machinery, enabling the development of advanced metal-processing plants.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_silk</key>
<text>We have secured a source of silk, allowing our textiles industry and buddhist sites to develop.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_acquired_tea</key>
<text>We have secured a source of tea, essential for entertainment establishments.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_coal</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of coal, putting an end to our planned rail network.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_copper</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of copper, preventing our development of strong ships and military ports.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_cotton</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of cotton, preventing further development of our textiles industry.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_iron</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of iron, putting an end to our planned advancement of dock facilities and ships.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_machinery</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of machinery, preventing us from further developing our metal-processing plants.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_silk</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of silk, preventing us from further developing our textiles industry.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_resource_lost_tea</key>
<text>We have lost all sources of tea, preventing expansion of the entertainment industry within our domain.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_your_army_bombarded</key>
<text>An enemy fleet bombarded one of our armies!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_your_settlement_bombarded</key>
<text>An enemy fleet bombarded one of our cities!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_campmap_your_slot_bombarded</key>
<text>An enemy fleet bombarded one of our provinces!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_character_gains_level_general</key>
<text>This general is ready to develop his skills, having honed his ability to command.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_clan_level_increase</key>
<text>Owing to our modernisation efforts, we are now able to further develop our clan's military technologies and civil policies.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_copy_protection_message</key>
<text>PLACEHOLDER@#~!We have detected that the game executable has been tampered with and is likely to fail if you continue playing. This is usually due to an attempt to play a pirated copy of the game, but may in some cases be caused by a virus or cheat program.  If you own a genuine copy of Total War™: SHOGUN 2 - Fall of The Samurai please exit the game, verify your game cache in Steam, scan for viruses and disable any cheat programs you are running.  If you do not own a genuine copy of Total War™: SHOGUN 2 - Fall of The Samurai please purchase one from http://store.steampowered.com/app/34330/.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_emergent_faction</key>
<text>From the ashes of war, a new clan rises to ride into history!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_faction_destroyed</key>
<text>Even the mightiest of clans are insignificant when facing our own!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_faction_destroyed_them</key>
<text>A powerful clan has been crushed. Now their bodies are food for the carrion!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_railway_blocked</key>
<text>An enemy force is blocking a railway which our forces would otherwise be able to use for transport; they will need to be defeated or chased away before transit may resume.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_railway_sabotaged</key>
<text>The enemy has damaged one of our railway stations; transit across the province will not be possible until repairs have been made.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_railway_theirs_first</key>
<text>Another clan has established Japan's first railway connection! This advanced method of transport allows armies and agents to move quickly between interconnected provinces; we would surely benefit from developing our own rail network.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_railway_yours_first</key>
<text>We have established Japan's first railway connection! This advanced method of transport will allow us to move armies and agents quickly between interconnected railway stations, as long as they belong to us or to a clan with whom we have agreed military access.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>bos_tech_advance</key>
<text>\n</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_constructed</key>
<text>Construction of the following building is complete:</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_their_legendary_begins</key>
<text>One of our rivals began construction of a legendary building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_their_legendary_built_first</key>
<text>All Japan looks in awe at the legendary building our rivals have completed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_your_castle_upgrade_ready</key>
<text>This castle reached its population limit. Increase its capacity through further construction.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_your_legendary_built_first</key>
<text>All eyes are upon us! Our achievement truly is the stuff of legend!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>building_your_legendary_built_not_first</key>
<text>The construction of a legendary building is a matter of great pride. It is admired by all who see it.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_buddhist_revolt</key>
<text>The people, joined by monks, have risen up in revolt against us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_christian_revolt</key>
<text>The people are angered at their treatment and have risen up in revolt!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_clan_uprising</key>
<text>Once fiercely loyal, these samurai have rebelled against their masters!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_ikko_revolt</key>
<text>The people have risen up in revolt against us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_peasant_rebellion</key>
<text>The people have taken up arms against their rightful masters!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>camp_revolt_imminent</key>
<text>Tensions in this province are reaching dangerous levels. There will be insurrection if the people's anger is not appeased.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campaign_lost</key>
<text>Our lands have been lost! The clan's proud warriors now feed the soil.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campaign_lost_your_faction_destroyed</key>
<text>All hope is lost! The clan is no more; our warriors feed the earth!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campaign_won</key>
<text>All Japan bows before us! The daimyo has become Shogun, his authority unchallenged! </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_AI_backstab_warning</key>
<text>We have received disturbing news, my lord. Our sources within this once-friendly clan warn us that their daimyo, intent on exploiting our current situation, is now plotting to invade us. We must prepare for any hostilities!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_ashikaga_become_shogun</key>
<text>The puppets have been returned to power! The Ashikaga Shogunate rules once again.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_bankrupt_desertion</key>
<text>Deprived of their upkeep by our clan's bankruptcy, this unit has deserted.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_enemy_army_withdraws</key>
<text>Look at them flee, like rats before the hawk. The enemy army is in retreat!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_enemy_naval_invasion</key>
<text>The enemy landed an army on our soil.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_enemy_navy_withdraws</key>
<text>The enemy fleet withdrew from this battle.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_faction_encountered_them</key>
<text>A clan we have yet to come into contact with has scouted our territory. We can now begin diplomatic negotiations with them.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_faction_encountered_you</key>
<text>We have encountered a clan with whom we have had no previous contact. We can now begin diplomatic negotiations with them.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_food_shortage</key>
<text>There is a shortage of food in this province. Turmoil abounds as the populace struggle to sustain themselves.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_impending_deadline</key>
<text>Time slipped away from us! Little now remains for the completion of our objectives.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_kyoto_contested</key>
<text>The fate of Kyoto hangs in the balance! Two clans fight for control of the capital.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_prestige_emperor_acknowledgement</key>
<text>Word of our achievements have reached the imperial court; His Imperial Majesty now watches our exploits with interest. As we continue to conquer and secure great victories, so our clan’s fame will continue to increase. We must tread cautiously; the Shogun will not take kindly to any who might threaten his authority.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_prestige_enemy_threat_to_shogun</key>
<text>The influence of this clan is far-reaching. Their growing power concerns the Shogun.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_prestige_general_knowledge</key>
<text>Our exploits are talked of the length and breadth of Japan. The name of our daimyo is on everybody’s lips, uttered with awe and fear in equal measures. It will not be long before the Shogun decides to act against us; we must prepare ourselves for this eventuality.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_prestige_realm_divide</key>
<text>Japan stands in awe of our might! Rumours abound that the Shogun is rallying support in a bid to crush our clan out of existence. Our enemies and those loyal to the Shogun will surely fall in league with him - we cannot rely upon even our oldest allies for aid. There is little time; we must do everything in our power to prepare for the coming storm. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_prestige_threat_to_player_shogun</key>
<text>Our ever-growing renown makes the Shogun nervous; there are whispers upon the wind that he plots against our clan to halt our rise to power!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_religious_unrest</key>
<text>The people of this province do not share our religion; without action there could be insurrection!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired</key>
<text>We have acquired an important resource, allowing us advantageous new construction and recruitment opportunities.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_cotton</key>
<text>This source of excellent cotton allows us to provide warm, light and sturdy clothing for our people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_goods</key>
<text>Skilled craftsmen create beautiful goods, increasing both the inner and outer wealth of the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_iron</key>
<text>Making a great sword requires skill, patience and access to the right materials. This source of superior iron will reduce the cost of recruiting troops.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_silk</key>
<text>We have acquired a source of Chinese silk, fit for resplendent kimonos and other luxury clothing prized by entertainers and nobles alike.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_spices</key>
<text>We have secured a supply of the finest incense, a key element to performing Buddhist rites.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_stone</key>
<text>We have acquired a good source of stone, enabling the construction of superior castles and reducing local construction costs.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_warhorses</key>
<text>We have acquired impressive steeds, enabling us to radically improve the quality of our cavalry. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_acquired_wood</key>
<text>Not every tree is suitable for ship building. With a source of superior wood secured we can construct better ships.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost</key>
<text>We have lost an important resource to the enemy, barring access to certain buildings and units. Recapture should be a priority.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_cotton</key>
<text>Our cotton resource was lost, depriving the people of its benefits.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_goods</key>
<text>The loss of our high quality craft goods will affect the clan's wealth in every way.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_iron</key>
<text>We have lost our source of superior iron, affecting trade and recruitment costs.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_silk</key>
<text>We have lost our Chinese silk resource, affecting trade in luxury goods.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_spices</key>
<text>The loss of our incense resource will affect our ability to carry out our religious rites.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_stone</key>
<text>Without access to superior stone resources, we will be unable to construct great castles.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_warhorses</key>
<text>We have lost the source of our superior horses to the enemy, greatly reducing the effectiveness of our cavalry.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_resource_lost_wood</key>
<text>Losing our superior wood resources will affect the quality of our shipbuilding and prevent us from building military ports.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_they_adopt_christianity</key>
<text>In these times of turmoil people seek solace in religion. In its search for answers a rival clan chose to adopt Christianity.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_they_become_shogun</key>
<text>A rival daimyo has declared himself Shogun and claimed the power for his clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_they_meet_europe</key>
<text>Men have arrived from overseas to trade with a rival clan. Our agents tell us that the deadly new weapons they bring may tip the scales of power away from us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_they_renounce_christianity</key>
<text>In these tumultuous times opinions are as changing as the wind. This clan reverted to Buddhism, forsaking their Christian beliefs. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_vassal_province_acquired</key>
<text>Our vassal has successfully secured a province, thereby strengthening both our domains.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_vassal_province_lost</key>
<text>Our vassal has lost a province, thereby diminishing both our domains.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_adopt_christianity</key>
<text>The turbulence of the times calls for radical new concepts. As such, we embrace Christianity. This will affect how some clans view our own and has placed our daimyo's honour in doubt.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_become_shogun</key>
<text>Fear and wonder are a powerful combination that our clan has used to its advantage. All Japan stands in awe of our mighty Shogun, but we must tread cautiously; our enemies and those loyal to the former Shogun are sure to take arms against us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_captured_kyoto</key>
<text>A great prize indeed! Kyoto is under our control; we must hold it for a year in order to claim the Shogunate.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_lost_kyoto</key>
<text>Beautiful Kyoto is lost to us, and with it the seat of all power in Japan. We must recapture it!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_meet_europe</key>
<text>Men have arrived from overseas to trade with us. We can defeat our enemies utterly with the deadly new weapons they have brought to our shores.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_you_renounce_christianity</key>
<text>Renouncing Christianity in favour of enlightened Buddhism can only appease those who follow the old ways, but may anger the converted.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_your_general_assassin_wounded</key>
<text>This general's wounds were not enough to dispatch him. He has retired to convalesce, but will return to his duty when recovered.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_your_general_convalesced</key>
<text>Following a period of convalescence our general returned to duty at the clan capital.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_your_general_killed</key>
<text>An honourable death; no warrior can ask for more. The clan will mourn the loss of this great man.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>campmap_your_general_returns_to_capital</key>
<text>Our general was wounded in the thick of battle. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>ceasefire_declared</key>
<text>All animosity between our clan and our former enemy is forgotten. Peace has been brokered and all forces have returned to their rightful places.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>ceasefire_declared_them</key>
<text>These two great clans put their differences aside, declaring a new era of peace throughout the land.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_dies_natural_causes</key>
<text>This man reached the end of his days and met his death at peace.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_dies_natural_causes_female</key>
<text>This blossom of the clan fell from our family tree, meeting her death with the same grace she showed in life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_dies_navy_destroyed</key>
<text>This noble warrior died whilst serving aboard one of our ships.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_dies_suspicious</key>
<text>This man died at the hands of an enemy agent! We must apprehend the culprit behind this heinous crime!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gain_level</key>
<text>This man proved himself and received promotion as a result.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_geisha</key>
<text>This geisha is ready to develop her skills, having refined her aptitude for assassination.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_general</key>
<text>This general is ready to develop his skills, having honed his ability to command through fighting the clan’s enemies.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_ikko_monk</key>
<text>This Ikko monk is ready to develop his skills, having fanatically devoted himself to the practice of his Jodo Shinshu beliefs.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_metsuke</key>
<text>This metsuke is ready to develop his skills, having honed his abilities through the execution of his lord’s justice.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_missionary</key>
<text>This missionary is ready to develop his skills, having fervently devoted his thoughts for the benefit of the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_monk</key>
<text>This monk is ready to develop his skills, having diligently devoted his thoughts for the benefit of the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>character_gains_level_ninja</key>
<text>This ninja is ready to develop his skills, having perfected his mastery of ninjutsu by carrying out his lord’s wishes.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_birth_summary</key>
<text>The birth of a child is always a joyous occasion, but when a family is blessed with multiple children it is cause for celebration indeed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_brother_comes_of_age</key>
<text>Today, a boy becomes a man. Our lord's kin has come of age and is ready to fight at his brother's side. We have seen the beginnings of a fine general.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_character_commits_seppuku</key>
<text>This man committed suicide at his lord's command, so preserving his family's honour.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_character_defects</key>
<text>This man abandoned the clan! The maintenance of loyalty is vital and should be considered at all times.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_character_disgraced</key>
<text>Dishonour on his family! This man's defection is a great insult to the clan, his family have been expelled forthwith. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_character_disloyal</key>
<text>This man's loyalty is waning. Investigation by metsuke or the offer of marriage may bring him back into the fold.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_character_executed</key>
<text>Death before dishonour! This man was executed as an example to others who would betray the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_daimyo_killed</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our noble lord was struck down by the enemy in the heat of battle! His loss will be mourned greatly.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_daughter_born</key>
<text>A new daughter is born to the clan. May she bring peace and serenity to the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_daughter_comes_of_age</key>
<text>This beautiful flower blossomed and is now ready to marry. Choose her suitor wisely, she can ensure loyalty to the clan or seal good relations with another.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_enemy_character_defects</key>
<text>This general turned on his former masters and joined our cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_enemy_clan_family_destroyed</key>
<text>This clan’s ruling family has been eradicated. A distant relative has stepped forth to assume the mantle of daimyo and - for the time being - their clan’s future is secured. However, the turmoil following the loss of their daimyo and his kin will has left the clan vulnerable. We may wish to capitalise on this turn of events.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_enemy_daimyo_killed</key>
<text>Our honoured foe fell in battle, now sitting with pride amongst the ancestors.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_daimyo</key>
<text>Our daimyo chose a wife from the family of one of his trusted retainers. Their union will cement the bonds of loyalty within the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_daimyo_diplo</key>
<text>The daimyo chose to unite our clan with another through marriage, easing the tensions between us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_daughter</key>
<text>A faithful general was rewarded with marriage to the daimyo's daughter. This will only increase his loyalty to the clan. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_daughter_diplo</key>
<text>A good son accepts the marriage proposed by his father. By marrying the daimyo's son to the daughter of a rival leader diplomatic relations between our two clans are greatly improved.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_son</key>
<text>A day for celebration! The daimyo's son married the daughter of a loyal retainer, only strengthening the bonds of loyalty within the clan.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_marriage_son_diplo</key>
<text>The daimyo is dead! The love of a woman can calm even the most ferocious of men. The daimyo's daughter married into a rival clan as part of a diplomatic deal.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_new_daimyo_brother</key>
<text>The daimyo is dead! Having left no heirs to continue his great work, the power of our great lord passes to his honoured brother. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_new_daimyo_general</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our honoured daimyo and his heirs have been destroyed by our enemies! With his dying breath, the daimyo entrusted the fate of the clan to his most trusted warrior and bestowed upon him the honour of bearing the clan’s name. The future of the clan has been secured - for the time being  - but the repercussions of our loss will affect the people for years to come.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_new_daimyo_heir_recruited</key>
<text>This is a day for celebration! Our erstwhile daimyo's honoured son has assumed control of both the clan and our futures.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_new_daimyo_heir_unrecruited</key>
<text>The daimyo is dead! Following the death of this honoured man his son has entered court life at the clan capital. Long may he reign!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_new_daimyo_retainer</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our honoured daimyo and his heirs have been destroyed by our enemies! In the absence of male descendants our lord has been succeeded by a distant relative. The future of the clan has been secured - for the time being - but the repercussions of our loss will affect the people for years to come.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_other_daimyo_dies</key>
<text>The daimyo of another clan died. An honourable man, he is mourned by friend and foe alike. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_regent_retainer_hostage</key>
<text>A tragic day, for with our daimyo's death the succession is uncertain. A regent was appointed to rule until his son is released from captivity.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_regent_retainer_young</key>
<text>It is a time of mourning and yet the leadership of the clan is still uncertain. A loyal retainer was named regent until the daimyo's heir comes of age.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_regent_wife_hostage</key>
<text>Following the death of our lord his honoured wife was named regent until their son is returned from captivity.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_regent_wife_young</key>
<text>The daimyo is dead! His honoured wife will take control of the clan's interests until their son comes of age. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_son_born</key>
<text>Every man needs an heir to continue his work when his time of dissolution arrives. Male children are a blessing that will secure the family line in the future.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_son_comes_of_age</key>
<text>Today, a boy becomes a man. Our lord's son has come of age and is ready to fight at his father's side. We have seen the beginnings of a fine general.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_their_hostage_executed</key>
<text>Our diplomatic agreement with another clan was broken prematurely. The life of their kin, held hostage by us as part of that agreement, is now forfeit.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_their_hostage_returned</key>
<text>No longer of use to us, this hostage was returned to their clan:</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_their_hostage_taken</key>
<text>Crippling a man's heart is far more effective than crippling his army. A young hostage was taken to assure the outcome of our diplomatic negotiations.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_worthy_bride</key>
<text>A loyal retainer offers his daughter's hand in marriage; will this man take her as his bride?</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_your_hostage_executed</key>
<text>Our kin has been put to the sword by his captors following a premature break in the diplomatic agreement between our clans.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_your_hostage_given</key>
<text>Sometimes a man must sacrifice those things dearest to him for the greater good. A member of your family was made a hostage as part of a diplomatic deal.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>clan_your_hostage_returned</key>
<text>This hostage has been released and returned to us by the following clan:  </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>copy_protection_message</key>
<text>You have loaded a game saved without an authentic copy of Total War: Shogun 2 installed. Consequently, the game may become unstable. To purchase a copy please visit http://store.steampowered.com/app/34330/.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>emergent_faction</key>
<text>From the ashes of war rises a new clan. If left unchecked it may gather strength and rise to challenge us one day.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_destroyed</key>
<text>Even the mightiest of clans are of little consequence when faced with the power of our own!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_destroyed_minor</key>
<text>These insignificant insects were wiped from the face of the earth! </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_destroyed_them</key>
<text>A powerful clan has been destroyed by a rival. Now the bodies of their warriors are food for carrion!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_destroyed_them_minor</key>
<text>The weak will always be crushed by the strong. A once-great clan was destroyed utterly. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_joins_war</key>
<text>War is like a tornado, consuming everything in its path. A clan has joined its allies to fight a mutual enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>faction_joins_war_against_player</key>
<text>Treachery! This clan joined our enemies in their war against us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_bribe_critical_fail</key>
<text>This junsatushi was caught attempting to bribe our men. He will never bribe another man again.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_bribe_fail</key>
<text>The respect our men have for their lord prevented the enemy from bribing them.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_bribe_success</key>
<text>Treachery! Our men have joined the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_payoff_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy junsatsushi attempted to pay-off one of our agents, but was caught and executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_payoff_critical_success</key>
<text>Shameful! Having been paid-off by an enemy junsatsushi, one of our agents abandoned his lord.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_payoff_fail</key>
<text>True to our lord and master, this agent refused an enemy junsatsushi's payoff attempt.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_request_ally_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy junsatsushi who sought the allegiance of those loyal to our cause has been put to the sword.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_request_ally_fail</key>
<text>An enemy junsatsushi attempted to secure the allegiance of our subjects. None have been tempted, but the enemy remains at large.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_request_ally_success</key>
<text>Treachery! One of our provinces has abandoned our cause to throw their lot in with the enemy!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_enemy_request_ally_success_partial</key>
<text>An enemy junsatsushi attempted to secure allegiance in one of our provinces. Some of our garrisoned forces betrayed us and joined his cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_bribe_critical_fail</key>
<text>This man failed us. Caught attempting to bribe the enemy, he was summarily put to death. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_bribe_fail</key>
<text>This man lacks even the wits to bribe a common soldier! Let us hope this isn't a common occurrence. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_bribe_success</key>
<text>Even the most virtuous have their price! Our silver-tongued junsatsushi bribed rival forces to join us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_payoff_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our junsatsushi was executed attempting to pay an enemy agent to abandon their master.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_payoff_critical_success</key>
<text>An enemy's dishonour is indeed cause for celebration. Our junsatsushi successfully paid a rival agent to abandon their lord, thereby weakening our enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_payoff_fail</key>
<text>It seems that money cannot buy everything. An enemy agent resisted our attempt to pay him off.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_request_ally_critical_fail</key>
<text>The loyalty of some knows no bounds. Our junsatsushi failed to convince the people of this province to join us. His reward was death at their hands.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_request_ally_fail</key>
<text>Our junsatushi failed to secure the allegiance of this province and its people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_request_ally_success</key>
<text>None can deny that ours is a noble cause! We have secured the allegiance of this province and those who swore to defend it.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_jun_yours_request_ally_success_partial</key>
<text>Our junsatsushi was unable to rally the people of this province to our cause. Nevertheless, some of the garrison have sworn themselves to our banner.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_seduce_critical_fail</key>
<text>A woman's wiles are no match for one's loyalty to their lord. This enemy shirabyoshi was executed for attempting the seduction of our subject.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_seduce_critical_success</key>
<text>Deplorable! One of our subjects was seduced by an enemy shirabyoshi. Now he serves her lord.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_seduce_fail</key>
<text>An enemy shirabyoshi attempted to seduce one of our subjects. Loyalty has prevailed, but we must be vigilant.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_stall_critical_fail</key>
<text>A rival shirabyoshi was captured and executed whilst attempting to distract our troops.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_stall_critical_success</key>
<text>Some men's hearts are weak. An enemy shirabyoshi successfully distracted our troops.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_enemy_stall_fail</key>
<text>A rival shirabyoshi was seen attempting to distract our troops. Utterly devoted to their duty, they were not swayed by her performance.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_seduce_critical_fail</key>
<text>Tragedy! Our shirabyoshi was murdered for attempting the seduction of an enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_seduce_critical_success</key>
<text>Our shirabyoshi successfully seduced an enemy. He has abandoned his former master and sworn fealty to our lord.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_seduce_fail</key>
<text>Not all are swayed by a lady's charm. Our shirabyoshi falied to seduce an enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_stall_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our shirabyoshi failed to distract the rival army and was executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_stall_critical_success</key>
<text>Our shirabyoshi successfully distracted the rival army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_shi_yours_stall_fail</key>
<text>Our shirabyoshi failed to distract the rival army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy sou attempted to demoralise our troops. He was executed as an example to others. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>Despite enemy attempts to demoralise our forces, they remain ready to fight to the end.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>Damnation! Our army was demoralised by an enemy sou.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>The enemy sent a sou to foster dissent in our province. With failure his life is forfeit.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_incitement_fail</key>
<text>An enemy sou attempted to seed dissention amongst our people, but their loyalty never faltered.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_incitement_success</key>
<text>An enemy sou spread dissent throughout this province! The people have risen against us!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>The downfall of this enemy sou was his failure to break the resolve of our subject. He was executed for the crime.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>One of our agents turned his back on the clan following conversations with an enemy sou.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>Despite the best efforts of the enemy, our agent stuck to their convictions.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_enemy_persuasion_success</key>
<text>Having had a crisis of conscience, this agent retreated to a place of solitude.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_demoralisation_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our sou was caught attempting to demoralise an enemy force. He has been executed.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_demoralisation_fail</key>
<text>Our sou failed to spread despair amongst the enemy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_demoralisation_success</key>
<text>Words are as powerful as weapons. Our sou caused enemy troops to doubt their leadership.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_incitement_critical_fail</key>
<text>This sou was executed for attempting to incite unrest within enemy lands.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_incitement_fail</key>
<text>No amount of persuasion could convince the people of this province to rebel against their masters. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_incitement_success</key>
<text>Chaos reigns! Our sou successfully incited a revolt in this province.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_persuasion_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our sou was executed for trying to persuade an enemy agent to enter retire.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_persuasion_critical_success</key>
<text>Those uncertain of their beliefs are easy to lead astray. Our sou successfully convinced an enemy to abandon their cause.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_persuasion_fail</key>
<text>Some are too closed-minded to aspire to enlightenment. We failed to indoctrinate this enemy agent.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_sou_yours_persuasion_success</key>
<text>This enemy agent retired to reconsider his path to enlightenment.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was apprehended and executed following an assassination attempt.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>One of our subjects met their end under suspicious circumstances. There is no mistaking the hand of the enemy in this event.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_assassin_detected</key>
<text>Our men detected the presence of a rival monomi. We must be cautious.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_assassin_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was detected whilst attempting the assassination of a man loyal to our family.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_assassin_success</key>
<text>The enemy attempted to assassinate a member of our clan! Having succeeded only in wounding them, the assassin has now escaped. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_sabotage_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage one of our buildings.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_sabotage_critical_success</key>
<text>A building was sabotaged by an enemy monomi. The culprit escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_sabotage_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was detected attempting to sabotage our building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_subvert_critical_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage our army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_subvert_critical_success</key>
<text>Some men's hearts are weak. An enemy monomi successfully sabotaged our army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_enemy_subvert_fail</key>
<text>An enemy monomi was spotted moving amongst the men! Early detection prevented any misfortune from befalling the army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_assassin_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi failed to eliminate his target. He was caught and executed whilst trying to escape.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_assassin_critical_success</key>
<text>Our monomi successfully assassinated his target, using all the strength and cunning available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_assassin_detected</key>
<text>Our monomi was detected by agents of another clan. He may now be vulnerable to their machinations.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_assassin_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi failed to eliminate his target and was detected, managing to escape the clutches of the enemy and a certain death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_assassin_success</key>
<text>Although unable to kill his target, our monomi wounded his adversary, putting him out of action for a while.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_sabotage_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi failed to sabotage his target. He was captured and summarily executed. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_sabotage_critical_success</key>
<text>Our monomi successfully sabotaged his target, using all the subversive skills available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_sabotage_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi has been detected whilst attempting to sabotage an enemy building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_subvert_critical_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi failed to sabotage his target army. He was caught and executed out-of-hand. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_subvert_critical_success</key>
<text>Our monomi succeeded in sabotaging the enemy army and escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_agent_spy_yours_subvert_fail</key>
<text>Our monomi failed to sabotage the enemy army and was detected, managing to escape with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_campaign_won</key>
<text>Glorious! The people of Japan have been united beneath our banner; the tale of our ascension will be spoken of for generations to come!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_campmap_prestige_threshold_one</key>
<text>Our successes have been many. Our worth and potential are now recognised by the people.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_campmap_prestige_threshold_three</key>
<text>We have grown powerful indeed, my lord. All now fear our potential; we must expect to face mounting opposition in the coming years.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_campmap_prestige_threshold_two</key>
<text>Our reputation preceeds us. Word of our family's exploits spreads far and wide, uttered with awe and respect.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_character_gains_level_dancer</key>
<text>This shirabyoshi is ready to develop her skills, having worked her magic on friend and foe alike.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_character_gains_level_inspector</key>
<text>This junsatsushi is ready to develop his skills, having honed his abilities through his service to the family.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_character_gains_level_monk</key>
<text>This sou is ready to develop his skills, having diligently devoted his thoughts for the benefit of the family.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_character_gains_level_spy</key>
<text>This monomi is ready to develop his skills, having perfected his clandestine abilities by carrying out his lord’s wishes.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>gem_enemy_of_the_state</key>
<text>Power breeds fear among the weak. Fearful of our strength and influence, the imperial family has declared us enemies of the state. We must be prepared; no one can be relied upon to aid us, not even our sister family.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>internal_mission_cancelled</key>
<text>This mission was cancelled due to unforeseen circumstances.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>internal_mission_failed</key>
<text>We failed to complete this mission in the allotted timeframe.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>military_access_cancelled</key>
<text>This clan has prematurely ended our military access agreement. Perhaps they mean to betray us?</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>military_access_expired</key>
<text>Our military access agreement with this clan has now ended. A new agreement must be brokered should we wish to continue unrestricted movement through their territory.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>military_access_prompt</key>
<text>Our military access agreement with this clan draws to an end. A new agreement must be brokered should we wish to continue unrestricted movement through their territory.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>military_tech_advance</key>
<text>Mastery of the arts improves our potential for military and civic development.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>movement_blocked</key>
<text>We are blocked from moving this way due to the presence of another. We must find an alternative route or attack them.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>placeholder</key>
<text>PLACEHOLDER!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>port_blockaded</key>
<text>Our fleet is blockading an enemy port, preventing trade flowing from the province.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>prestige_tech_advance</key>
<text>Mastery of the military and civic arts increases our standing amongst the other clans, proving our inherent superiority.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>recruitment_general_available</key>
<text>Loyalty is as priceless as any rare jewel. This man hopes to prove his by offering to command clan forces in battle.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>region_captured</key>
<text>This province is now under our control. Widening our grip helps to increase overall wealth through taxation and trade.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>region_captured_home</key>
<text>We captured the castle at the heart of enemy's territory, a crushing blow to their campaign and continued proof of our own limitless power!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>region_liberated</key>
<text>Having been liberated by a successful Ikko Ikki revolt, this province is now under our control. Some of the population surely remain loyal to their former masters; we must be mindful of local public order.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected</key>
<text>Our men detected the presence of a rival ninja. We must be cautious.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_escape</key>
<text>An enemy ninja was detected whilst attempting to assassinate a member of the clan!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_escape_army_sabotage</key>
<text>An enemy ninja was spotted moving amongst the men! Early detection prevented the poison of dissent coursing through the army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_escape_sabotage</key>
<text>An enemy ninja was detected attempting to sabotage our building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_execute</key>
<text>Following an assassination attempt we captured and executed an enemy ninja. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_execute_army_sabotage</key>
<text>An enemy ninja was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage our army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_detected_execute_sabotage</key>
<text>An enemy ninja was captured and executed whilst trying to sabotage one of our buildings.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_successful_army_sabotage</key>
<text>Some men's hearts are weak. An enemy ninja successfully sabotaged our army.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_successful_sabotage</key>
<text>A building was sabotaged by an enemy ninja. The culprit escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>spy_wounded_assassination</key>
<text>The enemy attempted to assassinate a member of our clan! Having succeeded only in wounding them, the assassin has now escaped. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>summary_resources</key>
<text>The ebb and flow of war has caused both us to gain and lose important natural resources. Essential to the economy and the business of war, we must strive to keep them secure at all times.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>trade_agreement_cancelled</key>
<text>Our relationship with this clan broke down to the extent that trade between us is cancelled forthwith.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>trade_agreement_cancelled_embargo</key>
<text>One of our former trade partners has broken their agreement with us at the request of a third party. They will pay for meddling in our affairs!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>trade_agreement_cancelled_port_loss</key>
<text>Continued trade between our clan and this valued ally is no longer possible.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>trade_route_raided</key>
<text>Our ships are raiding an enemy trade route, blocking the flow of money to their coffers.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>trade_route_raided_land</key>
<text>Raiding an enemy's trade routes prevents them making money from their resources.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>unit_recruited</key>
<text>A warlord is nothing without his warriors. Our new unit is ready to serve the clan. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>unit_recruited_ship</key>
<text>This impressive new ship will help us tame the seas to our will.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>war_declared</key>
<text>When words fail the only option is war. These two clans cannot reconcile their differences until blood has been spilled in their names.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>war_declared_you</key>
<text>This means war! Talk will not resolve our differences; the only remaining option is to put them all to the sword.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>war_declared_your_ally</key>
<text>When an ally is attacked it is dishonourable merely to stand back and watch the fighting unfold. We should support him in this latest endeavour.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>war_starving_out</key>
<text>The men defending this castle cannot hold out much longer; the people are starving and many lie dying in the streets. Surrender is imminent!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_army_destroyed</key>
<text>All have perished! Not a single man remains to carry our banner - it lies trampled in the dust.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_army_loots_settlement</key>
<text>To the victor, the spoils. We looted this province according to the rights of conquest, gaining our clan vital funds. Alas, this action has placed our daimyo's honour in doubt.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_army_retreats_region</key>
<text>Due to the state of our diplomatic relations with the ruling clan, our army was compelled to withdraw from their territory.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_bankruptcy_no_cash</key>
<text>The treasury is empty - the clan is using more money than is coming in through taxation and trade, consequently damaging our daimyo's honour.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_bankruptcy_upkeep_warning</key>
<text>The clan's finances are in a dire state, without drastic measures the clan will soon be bankrupt!</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_capital_lost</key>
<text>The heart of the clan has been ripped out by the enemy! Our capital is in their hands; the people at their mercy.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_capital_recaptured</key>
<text>We have reclaimed what is rightfully ours. The people are celebrating in the streets at the daimyo's return.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_fleet_destroyed</key>
<text>Our fleet was sent to the depths along with everyone aboard. Their spirits are destined to wander the ocean floor forever.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_port_blockaded</key>
<text>The enemy are blockading our port! This valuable resource must be taken back with haste, lest we lose vital trade income.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_region_captured</key>
<text>This province was lost to the enemy. The resources and income it provided are no longer available to us.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_settlement_besieged</key>
<text>Our castle is under siege! The defenders will hold out for as long as possible, but it will not be long before supplies run out and they are compelled to surrender. It is vital that they sally out to meet their attackers before this happens.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_slot_raided</key>
<text>The enemy raided our possessions. Any damaged buildings must be repaired if the flow of income is to be maintained.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected</key>
<text>Our ninja was detected by those in service of another clan. He may now be vulnerable to the machinations of enemy agents.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_escape</key>
<text>Our ninja failed to eliminate his target and was detected, somehow managing to escape the clutches of the enemy and his certain death.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_escape_army_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja failed to sabotage the enemy army and was detected, somehow managing to escape with his life.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_escape_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja has been detected whilst attempting to sabotage an enemy building.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_execute</key>
<text>Our ninja failed to eliminate his target. He was caught and executed whilst trying to escape.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_execute_army_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja failed to sabotage his target army. He was caught and executed out-of-hand. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_detected_execute_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja failed to sabotage his target building. He was captured and summarily executed. </text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_successful_army_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja succeeded in sabotaging his target army and escaped undetected.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_successful_assassination</key>
<text>Our ninja successfully assassinated his target, using all the strength and cunning available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_successful_sabotage</key>
<text>Our ninja successfully sabotaged his target, using all the dishonourable skills available to him.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_spy_wounded_assassination</key>
<text>Although unable to kill his target, our ninja succeeded in wounding and putting his adversary out of action for a while.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_trade_route_raided</key>
<text>Enemy ships raided a valuable trade route belonging to our clan. They must be destroyed before trade can continue there.</text>
</message_event_text>
<message_event_text>
<key>your_trade_route_raided_land</key>
<text>The enemy attacked a valuable trade route belonging to our clan. They must be destroyed before trade can continue there.</text>
</message_event_text>
</dataroot>